A Guide to the Harper-Hart Correspondence
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Harper-Hart Correspondence 1956 - 1975
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
ms-26
One Hollinger Box of processed materials
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Mrs.Hart
Biographical/Historical Information
The Harper-Hart Collection is composed of letters between two doctors who shared a belief in the use of the theory of evolution in the treatment of disease. The collection starts with a letter of Dr. Andrew Hart at UVa Hospital to Dr. Richard Harper in England on September 11, 1956. In the letter, Hart expressed his deep interest in Harper's paper,"Allergy and Other Stress-Condition Illness" that had been published in 1953. This letter as a beginning, they started to exchange their ideas as well as books and articles across the Atlantic for twenty years.
Realizing the persistence of the evolutionary origins in all diseases, Dr. Hart and Dr. Harper believed that "evolution" should be used by the physicians as it is backed up by people outside medicine. They thought that the physicians should apply the theory of evolutionary genetics to the established disciplines of the management of disease to find out the cause of disease and cure the patients.
Dr. Andrew Hart and Dr. Richard Harper were influenced by the evolutionist thinkers in this period such as George Crile, Lang Stevenson, George Gaylord Simpson, Theodosius Dobzhansky, Loren Eisley, and Ernst Mayr. Dr. Hart and Dr. Harper have inherited the ideas of these famous thinkers by exchanging their books and articles. With the inspiration from the thinkers as well as the encouragement and advice from Hart, Richard Harper published Evolution and Illness in 1961 and Evolutionary Origins of Disease in 1975. The preface to Harper? book, Evolutionary Origins of Disease well summarizes the belief shared by Hart and Harper: "I express my hope that colleagues, each in his own field, will use the theory of evolution to clarify our all too scanty knowledge of the origins of disease, to the better understanding of why our patients become ill, and to the more speedy relief of human suffering."
In addition to scholarly exchange, the two shared friendship: Dr. and Mrs. Hart visited Dr. Harper in England in 1961, and when Peter Harper, son of Richard Harper was working for the Johns Hopkins Hospital, Dr. Harp took care of him.
Dr. Andrew Hart, whose widow donated the collection, was Professor of Clinical Medicine and Director of the Student Health Service at UVa. He organized and developed the student health department at the University of Virginia in 1938 and served as head until 1973. He is also remembered as a pioneer in studying psychosomatic medicine.
Scope and Content
The collection contains 53 letters exchanged by Dr. Andrew Hart of UVa Hospital and Dr. Richard Harper in Devon, England from 1956 to 1975. In addition to the letters between Dr. Hart and Dr. Harper, the collection includes three journal articles, a letter to the journal editor, preface to Harper's book, Evolutionary Origins of Disease, summary of an unknown book, box list, glossary, and letters between Andrew Hart and Peter Harper, son of Richard Harper.
Arrangement
Files are arranged by chronological order.
Contents List
- 1. Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper September 11, 1956
- 2. Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart September 19, 1956
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart April 5, 1958
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper January 17, 1959
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart March 1, 1959
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper July 17, 1959
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart July 28, 1961
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart August 16, 1961
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart September 22, 1961
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper November 17, 1961
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart November 28, 1961
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart January 17, 1962
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper February 5, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart February 15, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart February 21, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart March 17, 1962
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper April 23, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart May 18, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart July 5, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart August 26, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart December 10, 1962
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper December 13, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart December 23, 1962
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart January 23, 1963
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart March 11, 1963
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart July 13, 1963
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart November 23, 1963
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper January 22, 1964
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart August 15, 1964
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper December 6, 1964
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart February 19, 1965
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper with a journal article by George Gaylord Simpson, "Organisms and Molecules in Evolution: Studies of Evolution at the Molecular Level Lead to Greater Understanding and a Balancing of Viewpoints," in Science, Vol.146, Number 3651, December 18, 1964. July 13, 1965
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart October 19, 1965
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper February 4, 1966
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart June 7, 1966
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart June 30, 1967
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper November 6, 1967
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper February 10, 1968
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart December 7, 1968
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper September 28, 1969
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart with a layout of a paper by Richard Harper, "An Essay on Evolutionary Paedomorphosis and Disease in Man." November 8, 1969
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart May 12, 1970
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper December 6, 1970
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart December 12, 1970
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart January 13, 1971
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper January 30, 1971
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper March 26, 1971
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper with a journal article by Ernst Mayr, "The Nature of the Darwinian Revolution," in Science, Vol.176, June 2, 1972 January 30, 1973
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart February 28, 1973
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper January 15, 1975
- Letter from Andrew Hart to Richard Harper May 17, 1975
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart May 25, 1975
- Letter from Richard Harper to Andrew Hart December 3, 1975
- A journal article by W. Proctor Harvey and Samuel A. Levine, "Paroxysmal Ventricular Tachycardia Due to Emotion: Possible Mechanism of Death from Fright," in The Journal of the American Medical Association, October 4, 1952. October 4, 1952
- Letters between Dr. Andrew Hart and Peter Harper, from September 29, 1969 to February 5, 1971 September 29, 1969 - February 5, 1971
- Letters to the editor, "Primordial Elements in Man," in The American Journal of Psychiatry, 127-7, January, 1971. January, 1971
- Preface to Richard Harper's book, Evolutionary Origins of Disease 1975
- Summary of an unknown book unknown
- Glossary of seven terminologies unknown
- Box List: Threats to Home Support unknown